the next talk is by aswin Paul bridging
biology and AI active inference for
biologically plausible decision making
models this is a 15minute
[Music]
video hello everyone uh my name is ashin
PA I recently finished my PhD from
monach University in Australia and is
currently working as a machine learning
researcher in versus AI so today I'm
here to talk about using active
inference to model biologically
plausible decision making uh and thank
you active inference Institute for
organizing this
Symposium let us start uh
by mentioning a recent Cutting Edge
experiment that was developed by
cortical labs in Melbourne so what they
managed to do is they developed a chip a
silicon chip and they cultured real
biological neurons like mice cortical
culture and human cortical culture and
they managed to couple this chip with a
computer game like the game of pong that
you see on the screen right now so the
experimental result is that given
meaningful feedback these neural
cultures actually demonstrate relative
improvement over time in playing this
game as you can see from this graph
right like the MCC and SCC neurons
actually demonstrate that they can
actually improve in game uh play when
compared to Baseline groups like the
silico um agent or the control group
groups so given such advancements in
experiments from a theoretical
perspective active inference is a great
candidate to model such experiments and
biologically plausible decision making
so we have emerging literature and a lot
of evidence um suggesting this so when
we actually try and do modeling there is
a clear need of scalability in the
active inference literature where we are
used to um modeling very small
environments with very low number of
states uh
and uh very low number of actions Etc so
in order to actually um use active
inference in such scenarios we have to
scale up the existing active inference
algorithms and in the first part of the
talk I will be talking about some
algorithms and techniques that we can
use to scale up modeling decision making
and active inference and in the second
half I will talk about using these
algorithms uh to actually model the
particular experiment that we saw
earlier so when we talk about um scaling
up active inference or scaling up
decision- making in active inference the
first technique I want to talk about is
evaluating um decision making backwards
in time and not forward in time as we
usually see in the active inference
literature so when we Define the
expected free energy um
and um compute which action should be
taken given a particular observation uh
rather than if evaluating expected free
energy or Computing It Forward in time
as we see in techniques like
sophisticated inference we can actually
use dynamic programming and model
decision making backwards in time and
this result is actually published in
paper uh in this particular paper if you
are interested in this particular
algorithm and a more General version of
this algorithm was recently published as
the inductive inference algorithm um by
um our colleagues in versus Ai and
um in that paper we note that um
inductive inference algorithm scale up
decision making drastically and can be
applied um to um bigger generative
models um another technique that we can
employ in this regard is to actually
learn prior preferences and in order to
do that we actually take um inspiration
from the optimal control literature uh
and this particular paper and this
particular paper introduces an algorithm
called said learning
that um improves um scalability and um
efficiently computes um the optimal
action um when compared to um Cutting
Edge algorithms like the Q learning
algorithm and a particular U Matrix in
this algorithm called the said Matrix um
is actually very similar to uh the prior
preferences in active inference and we
can actually learn this set Matrix
orders of magnitude more efficient than
um classic reinforcement learning
algorithms and what we do in in um in
this paper is that we show that we can
actually learn prior preferences using a
similar learning rule uh and once we
learn this prior preferences then
decision making is really easy because
we don't really have to plan a lot
forward in time and we also demonstrate
that learning is robust in this
particular algorithm and um talking
about computational complexity both
these methods one is DPF me method um
that computes um expected freeny
backwards in time and the other one that
um learns PR preferences are actually
orders of magnitude more efficient than
the classical active inference we see in
the literature or the recent um
sophisticated inference and both these
methods actually learn
um um or scales linearly with time uh
against the exponential computational
complexity of decision making that we
see in the active inflence
literature um so we tested these two
algorithms uh in terms of its
scalability and adaptability in um State
spaces um as high as 900 uh and what we
saw is that when we actually um
introduced stochasticity into the grid
these algorithms are more adaptable uh
than um Cutting Edge reinforcement
learning algorithms like din q and we
demonstrate that these algorithms are
scalable which gives us confidence is to
go ahead and model um experiments like
this and when it comes to modeling
neuronal Dynamics we already have
existing active inference algorithms uh
that model neuron dynamics that is from
um CBS ricken developed by professor
isur and colleagues and in one of their
Works they actually talk about um a
similar experiment where um neural
cultures are actually performing a
perception task uh which is called B
blind Source separation
and in a more recent work they also talk
about decision making in neural cultures
uh and um develop a decision-making
model uh that can be equated to neuronal
Dynamics so going into details um we
have this algorithm called
counterfactual learning algorithm uh and
uh they develop a version of the
variation free energy uh that is term to
term equivalent to a neural network cost
function uh and this is for a particular
class of neural network and more details
can be found in this particular paper
and there are two terms of interest uh
in this algorithm one is a Time
dependent risk parameter um and a Time
dependent State action mapping that this
particular agent um uses for decision
making and because of um how it is
developed it is biologically plausible
and can be shown that every term is
oneon-one related with the cost function
that a particular class of neuronal
networks actually minimize so in one of
our recent works we um generalized this
algorithm to have memory and we tested
it in a similar um control task like the
card P game that we see on the screen
and we can actually draw comparison with
the card Pole game and the pong game
because both of them are reactive task
uh where are where where the agent is
supposed to actually react to the
environment uh and take decisions
quickly uh to balance this pole or to
deflect the ball back um so we observe
that um compared to planning based
algorithms um like DQ and DPFE the
counterfactual learning algorithms
perform really well in this particular
um task and gives us confidence to go
ahead and model uh the biological um
neurons or the or the kind of
experiments that we saw earlier right
and in addition to being able to model
this uh we Al have um the advantage of
explainability in these algorithms
unlike um deep learning algorithms that
are black boxes so if we actually
perturb the environment say in a
particular episode we can actually see
that the risk term is shooting up in
that ex episode and um this um
particular term captures um changes in
behavior of the counterfactual learning
agent and we can actually try to explain
how decisions are being taken at every
time Point uh unlike blackbox approaches
so given these um several algorithms
that we have can we use them to actually
model um the manifestation of n natural
intelligence uh in experiments like dish
brain right so we for that we actually
develop uh an experimental based
generative model that is based on this
particular experiment so for example um
this is the pong game environment that
they use in the experiment um um prec l
so for example um we have the x
coordinate of the ball that being
communicated to the dish brain chip uh
through 38 distinct frequencies in the
experiment um and uh the y coordinate of
the paddle and the ball being
communicated through a different voltage
levels in the experiment um so for
example like we have three observation
modalities uh in this experiment and we
note that these are the number of states
and the ways of communicating that to
the agent and we um uh enumerate the
state space of our generative model um
using this experimental details uh and
match our generative model to be exactly
like um the experimental generative
process and we also have like the active
inference parameters um in our
generative model like uh the transition
dynamics of a pom DP uh and
counterfactual learning based State
action mapping the risk term and the
prior preference distribution Etc that
we discussed in the talk earlier and
given that we have this experimental
based generative model we can model
decision making um of in silico active
inference agent and hope to compare them
with the experimental result to draw
insights and so on right so first of all
we uh perform simulations using the
counterfactual learning agent uh and we
can see that counterfactual learning
agent um with memory Horizon um as low
as two is actually uh performing at par
with the HCC group in terms of
performance so here CFL um T stands for
um CFL memory Horizon T So as expected
with more memory Horizon it performs um
better uh and uh we can actually look at
um which memory Horizon is performing
similar to the experimental group and so
on and in one of our recent works we
note that the active inference are
incredibly data efficient compared to
deep learning methods and it is only the
active inference based model that is
counterfactual learning uh learning
method that demonstrate data efficiency
at par with the biological neurons when
compared to deep reinforcement learning
algorithms like a2c and po if you are
familiar with the Deep reinforcement
learning um literature um so we also
compare the planning based methods that
we mentioned earlier like the dynamic
programming method so in this particular
task or the pong game um planning is not
really useful so with increasing Horizon
of planning um we don't really see um
Improvement um
and um planning Horizon of five performs
as good as HCC neurons and planning
Beyond a point is not useful in this
particular task because of the nature of
the task and we also not um the
explainability of our models for example
if we look at the average risk um in the
counterfactual learning method we see
that the risk is actually only reducing
um significantly uh with a memory
Horizon of four and which and this can
also be correlated with the performance
Improvement that we saw um in the
results graph where with memory Horizon
4 there was a significant jump in
performance and these kind of
explainable insights um that can be
drawn from our models as a clear
advantage over black Mo methods like um
deep reinforcement learning uh and we we
can also look at um uh the entropy of
the CL parameters and we see that the
entropy is decreasing over time that is
um the evidence in learning and
parameters reveal um differences in
behavior of different agents and that is
a clear Advantage here and to summarize
um
we actually developed an experimental um
informed generative model and simulated
decision making in the particular um uh
environment uh we tested different
active inference based algorithms in
this setting and uh we
also uh noted the similarity of memory
augmented counterfactual learning method
um to the biological neurons and we are
interested in investigating similarities
um of the memory based CFL method more
the biological neurons and also insights
like this can Inspire more experiments
where um aspects like memory can be
studied well uh there are several um
limitations to this work where we
haven't conducted um a really um
involved statistical analysis in
comparing these agents we are right now
qualitatively comparing them um with um
average parameters uh but we would like
to do more statistical analysis uh and
we would also like to um
Inspire experiments from our theoretical
predictions in our future work so I
thank um all my collaborators in this
work and if you're interested in this
particular um work and the algorithms
that I discussed uh you can actually um
get access to all the papers here and uh
feel free to contact me if you have
suggestions or more questions about this
work so thank you for your time uh and
um I look forward to meeting you all
when when I have a chance next thank you
so much